Now that you have all your facts and supporting arguments grouped together in logical groupings, now you need to work on putting headlines to them.
The point here is to not just summarize what the headlines are, but actually synthesize. Get to a “so what?” Get to the deeper insight.
What is it that these things are really driving, creating, or doing? Why do they belong together?
As you get more senior in an organization, a summary is no longer sufficient. People expect synthesis, and it’s more critical for the kinds of messages you’re communicating.
So a lot of people confuse summary and synthesis.
Summary is actually a condensed version of all of the facts, right? We’re citing back the facts in a short form.
A synthesis, on the other hand, is actually getting the “so what” out of those facts. It’s essentially providing the insight that all of those facts together create.
It’s quite powerful, not only because it hits you hard with a key message and a “so what”,
but it also really tees up the implication, right? It really lets you then say: and therefore we should X.
So let’s say you’re going into a meeting with your CFO and you’re asking for additional resources. Let’s say you’re asking for additional sales resources because you actually want to grow your business in a certain region.
A summary statement that you might walk in with would say something like this:
the market is stagnating;
our competitors are investing in significant sales and marketing resources;
competitors are taking market share from us;
we haven’t invested over the past two years;
and consumer demands are changing, and they’re looking for more specialized expertise in the following areas, particularly on the sales side.
That’s a summary of all the things that are happening and going on in the market. But what’s the “so what”? The synthesis would actually say something like this:
we’ve had a struggling quarter because we have not invested to keep up with or surpass our competition in the market.
Right? And if you actually say a synthesis, it really tees up the ability to then say: and therefore we need the following amount in order to do X.
So what do you miss when you don’t synthesize? One is you miss the opportunity to give the audience the “so what”, the real nugget that you want the audience to walk away with in terms of what you’re saying.
Another thing you miss is the opportunity to present yourself as the expert in having thought this through, right?
If you give everybody the facts without the synthesis, or the summary without the synthesis, then you’re helping them come to their own conclusion, which is great,
but you don’t actually seem like the person in the room in command of the conclusion.
The third thing that you miss when you don’t synthesize is you miss the opportunity to essentially tee up the implication.
Right? A synthesis is really an opportunity for you to create the lead-in that then says: and therefore we should X. And that allows you to really make a compelling argument that people all follow.
So I was at a meeting recently with a colleague, and we were presenting to a senior executive some findings from a whole lot of analysis and work
that we had done. And my colleague was presenting really, really clearly the set of facts
that he had come up with, and they were quite compelling, and really, really good work. But halfway through the meeting, the senior executive looked at him and said:
“Okay, so sorry, what’s your point? Where are you trying to go with it? What are you trying to tell me?” My colleague essentially started backpedaling and got a little bit nervous, and
what was happening was three things. One is that my colleague had essentially lost the opportunity to provide the perspective, or the recommendation, on what he thought all of these facts meant,
right, the “so what”. He was missing that opportunity.
A second thing that was happening was, because of that, he was starting to lose a little bit of credibility with the senior executive.
And the third thing was he was making the executive feel a little bit like he was wasting his time.
The executive had that look in his eye that was: why are you telling me all this, and where is this going?
And all of those points and the facts that he was laying out were actually quite important to support the synthesis,
but because he had not led with the synthesis, they were actually starting to sound like just random points, and they weren’t necessarily coming together.